When it comes to fighting off cancer,
there are many variables at play. From
the cancer's location, the cancer type,
background health, and more. Recently,
it's been discovered that our microbiome
can influence our own cells to produce
more omega-3 fats, which ultimately
yields a better cancer fighting ability
in our body. But there's more to it than
that. For example, a critical reason why
some usually disadvantaged people
suddenly come out on top and what were
to happen if we bypass omega-3
production and go straight into
consuming it. Does that also work? Like
I mentioned, a lot goes into fighting
cancer and some people are more
resilient to cancer than others. One of
the reasons is due to differences in the
microbiome. the vast number of different
microbes, in this case in our gut. When
we take a microbiome from people with a
rich microbiome and transplant them into
mice, and we do the same with people who
have an identified poor microbiome, we
see some striking differences in the
cancer effect. We're looking at tumor
size with the rich human microbiome in
blue and the microbiome poor condition
in purple. If the lines go up, that
means a larger tumor. Not a good thing
in this context. Both conditions are
also given imunotherapy to help fight
the cancer. And even so, the rich
microbiome led to a noticeable
improvement, shrinking the tumor and
fighting back cancer. These kinds of
signatures are also true in humans. So,
up to now, it's a simple message. Early
evidence indicates a richer microbiome
helps fight against cancer. But that's
not why I enticed you to click on my
exceedingly shocked face for the
thumbnail. When we look at the molecules
coming from the microbiome, according to
this study that we've been relying on,
the microbiome releases molecules that
influence the activity of fat cells,
adiposytes. When the researchers look at
what kind of molecules are enriched in
the microbiome, they focused in on a
class of molecules called co-actors.
Essentially, these are molecules that
are necessary for enzymes to function.
So, if you have a molecule and you're
trying to produce another molecule, an
enzyme can speed up the reaction by
interacting with the initial molecule,
changing its structure into the new
molecule, the product. However, in many
instances, enzymes need co-actors to
function. So, when separating people who
have better cancer outcomes from those
that have poor cancer outcomes, we can
look at the differences in these
co-actors coming from the microbiome. In
this case, the co-actor is FAD. The blue
bars are people who are responders and
the gray are non-responders to cancer
fighting amunotherapy.
only FAD was highlighted as a molecule
different between responder status and
in fact when giving FAD directly which
by the way is flavin adinine ducleotide
originating from vitamin B2 to the same
scenario of mice with cancer bypassing
the microbiome entirely there's a
noticeable effect if the imunotherapy is
given the cancer is greatly diminished
but when FAD is also co-administered
there's an almost complete loss of
cancer. It should be noted though that
FAD alone does not combat cancer. So
this would mean that the effect is
dependent on a true cancer fighting
agent like an amunotherapy being
present. The point here being two
things. One, your microbiome encourages
the production of co-actors like FAD
that then two help fight against cancer
assuming that anti-cancer therapy is
also used. FAD coming from the gut can
enter the diposytes and influence their
ability to produce fat molecules. In
fact, when we look at the amounts of
these fat molecules comparing between
rich microbiome on the right and the
poorly diverse microbiome on the left
and we're measuring the ratio of
polyunsaturated fats to saturated fats,
we see a noticeable increase in
polyunsaturated fats. Now, keep in mind,
we're not consuming more of these fats.
So where are they coming from? They're
coming from these microbiome derived
molecules like FAD encouraging the
conversion of more fat molecules to
polyunsaturated fats. But not all
polyunsaturated fats are the same. And
it turns out that when we measure which
PUFAs or polyunsaturated fat molecules
are produced, there's a strong link to
increased omega-3s, particularly DHA or
docahexoninoic acid. And it's this DHA
that is believed to help fight cancer.
Now, fascinatingly, there are responders
and non-responders to cancer fighting,
possibly through this DHA mechanism.
What I mean by that is some people have
the microbiome capable of encouraging
the fat cells of the body to produce
more DHA fats which helps fight against
cancer. Now generally people who are
overweight tend to suffer from poor
health. And yet when looking at cancer
survival based on body weight, we see
some counterintuitive results. The
further up the lines remain, the more
people survived cancer over the measured
years listed as months on the horizontal
axis. Notice how the greenish blue line
remains above the pink line. That shows
that people who are overweight do better
than those who are normal weight. Now,
one big consideration here is that
certain cancers can manifest in body
wasting, which could influence the
results and skew them. However, the
researchers show a clear pattern that
the more overweight a person is, the
greater their chance of being a
responder to cancer treatment. Now the
reason for this responder non-responder
relationship is believed to be due to
differences in the microbiome for
multiple reasons not least of which
being that responders who are overweight
produce more FAD which doesn't occur for
anyone else. Now I don't think that we
can exclude other reasons but there's
definitely a notable relationship there.
In the end, we're talking about some,
not all, overweight individuals having
microbiome advantage in their ability to
produce FAD, which enacts a positive
role on fat cells, causing them to
produce more DHA, omega-3s, which is
believed to help fight cancer. Now, all
of this, assuming amunotherapy is also
in play. Of course, since all this
hinges on the end product, omega-3 fat,
uh why not just skip all the complexity
and just, I don't know, consume omega-3
fats? That would eliminate the guesswork
and it would also help people who don't
have this responder benefit through FAD,
normal weight and overweight alike. And
that's what was tried. And when looking
at tumor weight, again, again, the
higher the bars, the worse. And we use
different conditions. So nothing changed
our control and then only giving DHA but
no cancer treatment and then the cancer
treatment alone or the cancer treatment
with DHA. We see an almost stepwise
effect. Ultimately the combination of
cancer treatment amunotherapy plus DHA
omega-3 fat led to the best results. Now
this suggests that we could bypass the
FAD angle entirely. Though we don't know
that for certain as they didn't actually
add a fifth condition with FAD to tease
out the effects between the FAD and the
DHA if there are any meaningful
differences remaining. All in all, we're
seeing some preclinical evidence that we
can emphasize DHA fats, omega-3s with
amunotherapy and have increased potency
against cancer. Now, unfortunately,
while the main study that we've been
unpacking mixes human evidence with
animal evidence to give us this like
interesting relationship between gut
microbiome, fat tissue, omega-3s, and
cancer, they did not take the study that
final step to see if omega-3s might
track with improvements in cancer
outcomes when people are given
amunotherapy to combat their cancer.
Now, fortunately, we don't need to rely
on this study alone because I discovered
that there is such a study that looks at
this very issue. If we look at blood
omega-3s in people with cancer, do we
see better survival? Now, before I
divulge the exciting or disappointing
results, if you're looking for a more
in-depth analysis, including how FAD and
omega-3s act as anti-cancer molecules or
the different strains of bacteria
believed to be part of this healthful
responder class of people, then check
out the Physionic Insiders. It's my
premium research platform filled with
well over 100 videos at this point,
accompanying articles with those videos,
one paragraph summaries, a private
podcast, and honestly so much more. If
you're interested, just check it out
using the link in the description. Well,
don't look at me. I'm not going to do
all the work for you. Look for yourself.
The lower the bars go, the worse. As in,
fewer people survived their cancer.
Unfortunately, we're looking at ratio of
EPA, that's an omega-3 fat, over
arachidonic acid, that's on the left,
and the right is our DHA omega-3 fat.
Now, clearly having a high ratio, as in
more omega-3s, correlates with improved
cancer survival. And I'll even add that
these data are adjusted for body weight.
So, this falls in line with the previous
research. This was a small study. It was
a pilot study. So, I wouldn't consider
this the end all be all, but it's nice
to see a through line into the human
data from that last section from the
main study that we've been reviewing. In
the end, this is giving us signals that
having a higher omega-3 content in your
cells and in your blood relates to
better cancer outcomes when you already
have cancer. This is however also in the
context of already treating the cancer
with amunotherapy. I am certainly not
claiming that we have any strong
evidence that omega-3s can fight cancer
on their own. None of the data that we
went over showed that definitively. Even
here, I'd welcome more data because
we're in early days. But it is certainly
encouraging. I don't know, maybe in the
future we might see a randomized control
trial looking at omega-3
supplementation, the responsiveness to
imunotherapy in people with cancer. That
would be another piece of data that we
that would actually be really helpful to
solidify this all. Right now, I don't
see a reason not to consume omega-3 rich
foods like fish or even supplement if a
person has cancer. But there's plenty of
unanswered questions like does it matter
which cancer? Does it matter on the
stage of cancer? Does a person's general
health matter? And more so just
understand this is encouraging but not
yet definitive. And I mean what a cool
mechanism. Anyway, I've covered many
times over the benefits of omega-3 fats.
Check out the other benefits right here.
Thanks for nerding out with me. I'll
catch you in the next one. And I'm
wearing a nice shirt and tie because I
just got back from a